Fedora 项目的使命是作为一个协作的社区\n来引领自由与开源软件及内容的进步。
It was always intended to be a two-way street
我们始终期许它
between Red Hat and the open source development community.
成为红帽和开源开发社区之间的「双向车道」。
It's been 10 years.
十年磨一剑。
I mean, that's been a pretty long chunk of Red Hat's history.
在我眼中，那是红帽历史中浓墨重彩的一笔。
When we had recently announced Fedora,
当我们刚刚宣布 Fedora 的时候，
and we had an entire world full of people who didn't know what that meant,
所有人都不知道那意味着什么，
and we sort of didn't either.
我们自己甚至都有些不清楚。
We needed a name.
我们需要一个名字。
Something that would be evocative of Red Hat what we are,
能够让人回忆起曾经的Red Hat，
yet not used the Red Hat trademark.
但是并不使用红帽的商标。
And so we thought
所以我们想，
"you know, that fedora thing. That's actually kind of useful"
"你知道，软呢帽（fedora），的确有些用。"
Basically we had a product at Red Hat Linux
从根本上来说，
that was trying to do to perform two duties at the same time.
Red Hat Linux 是一项尝试同时胜任两种任务的产品。
It was trying to be enterprise software
它既要成为企业级软件，
and it was trying to be cutting-edge
同时又要紧跟前沿
"release early, release often" at the same time.
"尽早发行，时常更新"。
And once the business realized that
当公司意识到
those were two conflicting goals
这是两个相互冲突的目标时，
they made the move of splitting in to Red Hat Enterprise Linux
他们决定推动拆分为
which things would support over a long period of time,
提供长期支持的红帽企业版 Linux,
and then the Fedora project,
以及快速迭代并创新的 Fedora 项目。
which would iterate rapidly and make changes, would be innovatived of.
Back in the Red Hat Linux days
回顾 Red Hat Linux 的时代，
Warren Togami and other members of the Red Hat Linux community
Warren Togami 和其他 Red Hat Linux 社区的成员
set up a site called fedora.us.
创建了一个叫作 fedora.us 的网站。
It was add-on packages for Red Hat Linux
它原本是 Red Hat Linux 上的一组扩展软件包。
I proposed to Red Hat at the time
我当时向红帽提议:
"Hey, I have this thing called Fedora".
"嘿，我给它取名叫 Fedora " 。
That obviously was named to be related to Red Hat in some way
这样命名很显然与红帽有关，
like it's really build upon and grow Red Hat.
就像它确实也是生于红帽、长于红帽。
The history of Fedora really was the evolution
Fedora 的历史真的是
of what I still think today is the best large-scale
全球最好的大规模开源开发平台的进化,
open-source development platform in the world.
直到今天我依然这样认为。
I was astounded,
不得不惊叹，
like maybe two or three years later,
（项目发起）两三年之后，
you could look at the chart of
Fedora 贡献者就已经数以千计。
the Fedora contributor accounts that was in the thousands.
I think Fedora is the starting course
我认为 Fedora 是开源社区的「排头兵」。
of the open source community.
It is the platform
它作为一个平台，
that sets the pace of how quickly we can move forward.
定义了我们可以多么快速地前进。
It is a source code base
它包含超过两亿行代码的开源软件，
of over 200 million lines of software
which moves forward faster
发展速度快于我所知道的任何企业级产品。
than any enterprise class product that I know of.
I think if you had to look at Fedora five years ago
我认为如果你五年前观察 Fedora,
that you probably wouldn't see the Fedora of today.
你很可能预见不到今天的 Fedora。
So Fedora community is pretty vast
Fedora 社区蔚为壮大，
and we have people all over the world.
我们有来自世界各地的成员。
But I think a lot of people don't realize
但是我觉得很多人
all the things that go on behind the scenes.
并不清楚幕后的事情。
Fedora is essentially our open innovation lab
Fedora 实质上是我们的开放创新实验室，
and this is critically important to Red Hat's success.
它对红帽的成功至关重要。
People really get that there is definitely a relationship.
人们的确明白红帽与 Fedora 必然有种联系。
A lot of people do look to Fedora to
很多人都尝试从 Fedora 上
you know get a view of what's coming in a future version
对红帽企业版 Linux 的未来版本一窥究竟。
of Red Hat Enterprise Linux.
What Fedora did do
Fedora 做的事
was it gave a regularity to the innovation cycle
就是它为创新闭环提供了一种规律性，
that made it possible for other really large projects
使得其他大型项目
that had never played well with others to in fact play well with others
从单打独斗到众志成城成为可能
Red Hat takes a policy of everything goes upstream,
红帽采取的策略是一切推往上游，
"upstream first".
"上游优先"
And it's because we're passionate about the model,
这是缘于我们对这一模式的热忱，
we believe in the open innovation model and we're all in.
我们相信开放创新的模式并且我们也积极参与。
And for us Fedora plays a key role in that.
而且对于我们而言，Fedora 扮演着一个关键角色。
It's where we actually work with upstream communities
这是一个我们与上游社区实际协作的地方，
in a way where Red Hat is certainly involved
红帽一定程度上参与其中，
but we don't fully control.
但并不控制。
We have to work with and drive what we want
我们必须协作驱动一个
in an independent community.
我们所期待的独立的社区。
We could not make the kind of big bets
我们升级红帽企业版 Linux 时没有大风险，
that we make would we do a major update
of Red Hat Enterprise Linux
我们升级红帽企业版 Linux 时没有大风险，
without all the information and all the participation
归功于 Fedora 项目带来的信息、参与以及验收。
and all the acceptance that we get
because of the Fedora project.
归功于 Fedora 项目带来的信息、参与以及验收。
It's hard to say like "we're still here".
其实很难去说 "我们仍然如此"。
But I think that that in itself is a pretty decent success.
但是我认为从它本身而言已经相当成功了。
I mean we're approaching the 20th release of fedora
我是说，Fedora 经历了 20 个版本，
and we've done this every 6 months like almost exactly like,
而且我们过去已经坚持每六个月发布一次新版，
not perfectly clockwork but you know pretty darn close for ten years.
虽然也曾迁延，但最终还是坚持下来了。
And that's a long time to keep at something
长期坚持一件事情并不容易，
and be able to actually make something
尤其还要使之保持
that is useful and relevant and actually works.
有用、紧密相关而且切实可用。
I mean that in itself I think is a pretty big success of Fedora.
在我看来 Fedora 本身就是伟大的成功。
Fedora from the early years has always been about progress.
从早年间 Fedora 就进步卓越。
I am quite happy to see that after many years later
看到多年之后依然保持进步甚至加速发展，
that remains true, and continues to be accelerated
我由衷地感到欣慰。
I think it will continue being the place
我想它会继续成为
where a lot of awesome things that open source
优秀开源项目
actually come to either be developed
开发和展示的平台。
or they come to showcase what they've got.
Everything that we do is definitely got an element
我们所做的一切
of innovation to it
都一定会有创新元素，
that I think really sets us apart
正因如此，我们才与众不同。
I certainly owe a lot to Fedora.
Fedora 让我收获颇丰。
Frankly it's unclear I'd be at Red Hat if it weren't for fedora.
坦白来说，如果没有 Fedora，我都不确定我如今是否会在红帽。
Would I've been able to engage as well as I did
我加入红帽，
with the recruiter and ultimately Red Hat's board
乃至后来加入红帽董事会，
if I hadn't had that experience with Fedora.
都要归功于参与 Fedora 的经验。
So certainly it's near and dear to my heart.
我从心中深爱着它。
Fedora was vital for keeping Enterprise Linux relevant,
Fedora 功劳赫赫，它与企业 Linux 紧密关联，
for keeping it fresh,
保持青春活力，
and for giving us the ability to make innovative leaps,
给予我们创新跃迁的能力，
time after time after time
一直以来，矢志不渝。
是你们成就了今天的我们。
谢谢你，Fedora。谢谢精彩绝伦的十年。
感谢你们的坚持不懈，我们一起开创未来。
(视频摄制于2013年11月）